Rhiannon: Mental health services are
free on the NHS, but in some cases a
GP referral is needed to access them.
However, there are some mental
health services that allow
people to refer themselves.
At school or college, mental health
care can be arranged for individuals
through services such as CYPMHS
which we have discussed previously.
Leah: Some mental health problems
can be managed without the need of
approaching a GP and there are a
variety of materials available and
local organisations offering help.
Rhiannon: A GP will assess an individual’s
circumstances and offer appropriate
advice or treatment and can refer an
individual on to a psychological therapy
service or a specialist mental health
service for further advice or treatment.
These services may be provided
by a GP surgery, a large local
health centre, a specialist mental
health clinic or a hospital.
Treatment may be provided on a one-to-one
basis or in a group with others with
similar difficulties, and therapy
can also sometimes involve families.
Leah: An Individual has the legal right
to choose which provider and clinical
team they are referred to by their GP for
their first outpatient appointment and in
most cases, have the right to choose which
mental health service provider to go to.
Rhiannon: However, this right is not
there for urgent or emergency treatment,
where treatment and care is already
being received, if the condition isn’t
covered by that team, or the child
or young person is being detained.
some services available on the NHS
are for Psychological Therapies
anxiety and depression, eating
disorders, mental health services.
for alcohol addiction,
and for drug misuse.
Once a mental health service provider
has been decided on an appointment can
be booked through the NHS e-Referral
Service or via a doctor’s surgery.
Early access to mental health services
regardless of age, ethnicity, gender
or social status may reduce the
risk of problems becoming worse.